E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

RESUME

SYNOPSIS

A professional with more than a decade of International & domestic corporate experience of handling and managing Marketing, Operations, Strategy & New Business development portfolio in Fortune 500s,Indian Heritage MNC's & Small & Medium enterprises in ITeS,Telecom,Retail & Consulting organizations; from the traditional economy sector to Knowledge sectors of business.

And also experienced work in EMEA, APAC, India and APJ & SEA on corporate project assignments. In the last few years of his career, he has held mid-senior to semi-senior corporate positions. He has trained a large number of corporate managers in his career and has completed large training hours. He is a certified trainer on Six Sigma, Project Management, Management Consultancy and Customer Service Excellence. He conducts customized training programs in the Management skills areas He trains managers and executives in several management skills, soft skills & Consultancy.

He lectures in some of the country's B-schools and as a visiting Faculty in General & Strategic Management, Strategy, CRM and Marketing. He was involved in taking sessions in international Universities also during his corporate tenure.

As a consultant, he has worked with clients from Australia, Japan, USA, UK, and Singapore & Saudi Arabia in varied sectors like ITeS, Apparels & Merchandise, Education (Higher Studies) etc.

Scope of Domains Handled (Hands-on experience)

Marketing & BD,Sales,Operations & Delivery, Customer Service,SBU management, Training & Development, General Management, Vendor & Client management, SET-UP operations, Learning Management & Education.

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

WORK EXPERIENCE

Academic

Present Assignment (2014-Till date)

Reporting to MD

A large national player in education involved in coaching, guiding & counseling higher education student fraternity. The center under my authority is the <u>Centre of International Studies</u>. This centre guides, counsels and enables students for IB boards (O, AS, A, IBDP Levels), American Board (AP Levels), SAT I, SAT II, GMAT, GRE respectively. My target of student acquisition by May, 2015 is approximately 650+ students' for 3 centers.

The Academy, Co-Founder (2011-2014)

A coaching centre in Mumbai Suburban vicinity to cater to the students of IB, CBSE,ICSE, & the State boards for day scholars of IXth-XIIth grades. The institute provides coaching for streams for Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics, Biology & Economics. It had 300 students in total strength approximately.

Visiting Faculty, (2001-2012)

Delivering lectures in Graduation & Post-Graduation affiliated colleges in Autonomous and Private institutions accredited by AICTE and Mumbai University. I have had the opportunity of teaching/training/mentoring in several A+ & the top most ranking B-schools & Adult education programs for 2 year and PGPX program.

United World-School of Business – HOD & Faculty, General Management (February 2009-January 2012), Mumbai

Responsibilities: Primary Role

- ➤ Acted as HOD for General Management and Allied subjects. Foundation year subjects delivered: General Management & Fundamentals of Marketing and Specialization year subjects delivered: Marketing and Allied subjects & Entrepreneurship.
- ➤ Taught these subjects in Mumbai, Delhi & Ahmadabad.
- ➤ Coordinate, plan, organize, and instruct courses in the day, evening, or on weekends as assigned
- ➤ Initiate active at a high level of expertise in the subjects taught and stimulate enthusiasm for those subjects and ensure that each program/class contains essential curricular components, has appropriate content and pedagogy.
- ➤ Teach all classes according to an approved course syllabus and informed and updated concerning course content, requirements, evaluation procedures and attendance requirements.
- ➤ Ensuring students informed about their progress through the prompt grading of papers and other work.
- > To file an appropriate course syllabus for each course taught with the appropriate

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844 division chair and the Dean of Instruction's office

- ➤ Participate in program and curriculum review and development and student learning outcomes initiatives
- ➤ Organize each course taught into an effective instrument of learning
- > Serve as an academic advisor to assigned students & counsel as needed Secondary Role
- ➤ Assist with pre-registration and registration and to assist in the recruitment and retention of students
- ➤ Attend all faculty meetings, college assemblies, professional development and orientation activities, and other meetings as called by the Dean and Management.
- > Actively involved in the co-curricular activities of the college.

Adjunct Online Faculty of Global Leadership for Duquesne University, USA & University of Jamaica (February 2010-July 2010)

- ➤ Planning and preparing lessons; teaching across a range of qualification types and levels, in day or evening classes or open access workshops;
- ➤ Researching and developing new topics, courses and teaching materials, including online resources;
- ➤ Teaching large and small groups of learners from a range of backgrounds, abilities and ages;
- Monitoring, assessing and marking students' work;
- Maintaining accurate records and monitoring students' progress;
- ➤ Interviewing potential students and conducting diagnostic assessments as necessary; UnitedWorld-School of Business -Acting Dean for 2year PGPM program (August 2011-December 2011)

Responsibilities

Establishing and implementing the academic outcomes assessment and strategic plans, providing oversight and implementation of faculty evaluations and faculty appointments and academic support services including the library, the office of the registrar admissions, and student services.

- > Set and establish academic goals for the department to achieve and also maintain high standards in academics and teaching processes.
- ➤ Maintaining effective communication between students and faculty within the school or college and with other academic personnel.
- ➤ Act as a liaison between the students and the administration and between the faculty and the administration and responsible for hiring faculty members, evaluating college administrators and staff, budgeting, and setting academic rules and policies.

Students Activities (Few Achievements)

My contribution towards' Beyond the Classroom' Intervention Activities:

➤ Live Projects-On-site & Online

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

- Asynchrony learning PGPM & PGPX(full-time)
- > Student Welfare department
- ➤ Introducing new program topics

INSTITUTE OF RETAIL & FINANCE STUDIES –Consultant (Education Development & Operations), (January 2008- February 2009), Mumbai Responsibilities: Primary-role

Planning and executing the operations of the Institute including:

- ➤ Responsible for design and development of course structure along with detailed session plan in co-operation with the management.
- ➤ Faculty accumulation and appointing from industry, B-schools & experts.
- ➤ Maintaining standards/ quality control as per SOPs & Responsible for monitoring assessment processes Quality of question papers, setting up standards for evaluation of assignments and term-end examination, etc.
- ➤ Responsible for Academic leadership, excellence, International relation, publishing white papers, Improving brand image, etc.
- ➤ Initiatives / activities related to student placements, liaising with industry for brand building.

Secondary role:

The other general management role:

- > To seek business development to get desired numbers in terms of participants.
- ➤ To comply and report progress through system /other methodology put in use.
- ➤ To manage the overall operation of the training activities at the region & Coordinate with other faculty, sales team and central event management executive / team for adhering the set targets.
- ➤ Supervise the work and performance of the Admin marketing executive for effective performance of the training activities
- ➤ Follow the parameters highlighted in the work processes and target sheets shared Suggest value addition s in the contents and give feedback
- ➤ Help in identification of need areas to develop training programs for them.
- Marketing and promoting the institute.

Subjects Taught

- 1. General Management & Allied subjects, Entrepreneurship
- 2. Marketing & Sales management
- 3. Economics Macro, Micro & International Economics
- 4. Operations Management

Research Interests preference (in chronological order)

- 1. Management & Allied disciplines
- 2. Education & Philosophy

Papers Published

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

- ➤ 'Entrepreneurship and New Venture Creation', ICER-BRIC International Conference, IIM-Bangalore, 2011, International Journal of Management & Social Sciences.
- ➤ Others on Request

Other Academic Activities pursued

- ➤ Honorary Member of the Board Journal of Studies" (ISSN 2348 -3652), Gittaratan International Business School & FMS, DU (New Delhi), 2014
- Reviewer for International & National journals, 2012
- Set-up of Entrepreneurship department UWSB, Mumbai,2009-2012
- ➤ Designing of curriculum for PGPX & MDPs for professional people,2009
- ➤ Participation in the panel of NIT-Nagpur, GLIM, SPJIMR, BCIDS, Sinhgad Business School, KCIMS etc for student hiring/acquisition.
- ➤ Chairing of 'Knowledge management session' for SPJIMR-ICICI competition, 2007
- ➤ Participation of Module restructuring of IGNOU for Banking Retail,2006
- ➤ Participated and chaired training & education programs with the ongoing B-schools, 2012
- ➤ Volunteered as 'Academic Director' for International Institute of Marketing Professionals, Canada, 2012.

Corporate

HP (Global Services) Invent (February 2006 –January, 2009), Chennai-Head Account Delivery

My responsibilities involved being the global focal point for External Clients, Client Account Manager(WW process) and KPO/BPO's Delivery Organization (delivery centres, accounting process subject matter experts, transition, accounting service line) thus creating relationships with senior management customer for operational

excellence at local, country, region & Worldwide (WW) level to analyze delivery requirements & contribute to customer strategic business plan and strategize and processes with the customer in areas such as performance metrics and measure, escalation change management and communication. To ensure the true understanding of the delivery of transaction performed and to experience customer perceptions of service delivery, to motivate and drive the accounting delivery organization in the meeting of customer expectations. My first driven accountability to the client is to initiate focus on their deliverables and service levels as input into the HP BPO processes to record benchmarks in SLA performance, reporting and operational review with the client ,Change control process , Escalation management, Issue resolution, Accounting process improvement & end to end accounting process, performance reviews of process in various Business Centres(spearheading APAC,EMEA& AMS regions), Root cause analysis of customer input to processes and proposal development to address potential problems. Secondly it is similarly important to drive cost management and cost reduction in delivery drives, standardization and performance, inputs to get global standards for accounting processes for optimal performance, creating standard methods/tools for client management, driving CIP through large number of headcounts. Thirdly ensuring delivery

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

remains customer focused (VOC, TCE), standards in a multi company environment and with customers in different locations of different cultural sensitivities. Lastly I was accountable of developing new business with customers, external clients and new markets throughout the three regions-extensively travelled during this period of my job tenure to understand different business approaches.

The LOB's were IT support, Consulting, Services & Telecom.

Wipro Ltd (December 2004-January 2006), Mumbai -Senior Manager Operations/AVP

The role requires doing business with clients in America of a leading BFSI organization (Fortune Company) through a team of specialized workers. The accountabilities of my profile were Customer Satisfaction (VOC), Cross Up & sell, Monitor Delivery services through the delivery model, Strategic Account Management and add incremental revenue growth for accounts acquired. Managing day-to-day relationships with clients and developing a deep understanding of their products and long-term business strategies was a key function of the job to drive, manage and execute operational efficiency programs formulated as a result of SLA targets and works with the senior management to identify operational efficiency programs that increase and enhance productivity in the business. Being a key member of the management team contributing to the leadership of the business, it was important to Liaise and collaborate with colleagues across other services businesses, particularly those in USA appropriately to view levels of consistency, knowledge sharing and joint proposition development.

The LOB's was Financial Services.

Netwisers Inc., (March 2002 – October, 2004), Manila, Philippines -Head Operations & Customer Service

Managed and built 2 successful contact centres and managed services in multi-site delivery under 'Third Party Outsourcing' and B.O.T 'Build Operate Transfer' up to 1000 FTEs with clients across business verticals covering emerging and developed economies. I was spearheading all day-to-day operations and took overall responsibility/accountability for the delivery of setting up the centre for business .I was responsible for the development, implementation, and integration of solution for our clients. My large team afforded me to manage and motivate a team of multi cultural composition(mainly from SEA) by handling of client queries and providing after sales support and analyzing detailed client requirements; identify problem areas; and provide effective business solutions to satisfy client requirements. I was instrumental in setting the complete SBU with strength of 500 people engaging in various business processes from varied sectors for successful revenue-generation business operations. During this tenure, I worked very closely with people coming from different Asian countries.

The LOB's were Telecom, Wireless Services & Sales, Financial Services and R&D.

Koshika Telecom Ltd., Usha Group, Noida-Manager (UP)-Customer Service Operations & Business Development
(February 1997 March 1998)

(February 1997-March 1998)

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

Managed and built the Customer service operations department and service processes for one of the first GSM service providers of India, Koshika Telecom Ltd (Group Usha). My main focus was to Interact with customers to provide and process information in response to inquiries, concerns and requests about products and services, handle and resolve customer complaints, manage customers' accounts, keep records of customer interactions and transactions, communicate and coordinate with internal departments, account retention &follow up on customer interactions. I was responsible for the supervision of a staff of 40 people within the customer service department across the circles of operations-UP (West & East), Haryana & Bihar. The recruitment and T&D of the team was pursued by me to manage the needs/requirements of high revenue commercial accounts through extensive follow-up procedures and perform market research surveys amongst client base to seek feedback on sales techniques, follow-up methods and quality of after sales service which led to improving customer service base through the development of various new policies and procedures.

The LOB was Telecom & Wireless.

United Colors of Benetton, September 1992-December 1996 Delhi- Manager (Zone-South Delhi) –Customer Service & Retail

I have single headedly set-up and designed the company retail outlet from a scratch and tuned effective retail operations for the Apparel giant by maintaining operations by initiating, coordinating, and enforcing program, operational, and personnel policies and procedures. My job responsibility was complete store operational requirements by scheduling and assigning employees &following up on work results, maintain store staff by recruiting, selecting, orienting, and training employees by coaching, counseling, and disciplining employees; planning, monitoring, and appraising job results. My other functional accountabilities were to plan an overall strategy for the store(such as analyzing sales trends, recording sales figures and determining how to increase the store's profits),handle customer issues and building rapport with customers ,achieve financial objectives by preparing an annual budget, scheduling expenditures, analyzing variances, initiating corrective actions, maintaining inventories, formulate pricing policies by reviewing merchandising activities, determining additional needed sales promotion,

maintain stability and reputation of the store by complying with legal requirements. The LOB was Apparels and other Benetton Merchandise.

<u>Trainings Attended</u>

- ➤ World class 'Retailing Operations services' by <u>DOORS</u> in October, 1997.
- Customer Care Support Program" by <u>Kirloskar Institute of Management</u>, 1997.
- > CRM- Power Knowledge Series" by <u>AVAYA-TATA TELECOM</u>, 2002.
- ➤ "Fish philosophy" by Kari Kussy, HRD (AT&T), 2003.
- ➤ 'World Class Customer Services' by Dale Carnegie Training, 2005.
- 'Organizational Development 'for Management by 'ROOTS'-2006

E-mail: pinghosh@gmail.com Mobile. No: +91 9930219844

➤ Black Belt Mentor workshop , Corporate forum ,QAI, 2007

AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS

- > 'Hp Operational Excellence Team', 2007
- 'Best Sales Manager, Netwisers Inc.,2004
- ➤ 'People Manager 'SMI, Netwisers Inc.,2004
- Customer service Excellence Award ,Group Usha, 2000
- 'Retailer Salesman of the Year' UNITED COLORS OF BENNETTON, 1996 EDUCATION

Academic

- > B.A. (Hons.), Political Science, Delhi University, 1996
- > Bachelor of Business Administration, Annamalai University, 1998

Professional

- > PGD in International Trade (Executive Program) Bhartiya Vidya Bhavan,1996
- > PGD in HRM(Executive Program), NMIMS-Mumbai, 1999
- Master's in Marketing Management, Pondicherry University,2000
- Project Management Professional, IIT- Delhi, 2006
- > Certified in Six Sigma, Benchmark Sigma Pvt.Ltd & Wipro Technologies, 2007
- ➤ Diploma in Management Consulting ,Institute of Management Consultants of India-Mumbai Chapter,2010
- Executive Program in Developmental Policy, World Bank Institute,2011 Others
 - ➤ World Class Customer Services' by Dale Carnegie, India,2005
 - > Introduction to Philosophy, The University of Edinburgh ,2014
 - ➤ Introduction to Mathematical Thinking, Stanford University ,2014

Other Information (DOB: 01/01/1972):

Schooling

- ➤ Korobosea International School (1980-86), NSW Education Board, Australia.
- > Sardar Patel Vidyalaya (1987-1993), AISSCE, Delhi

Areas of Interest: Traveling, Reading & Sports, Networking

Sports: Captained the School team in Football & Volleyball in 1989–1990. Still indulge in Community sports like Football, Volleyball with the beach boys.

Personal (Family)

Father- Prof.Patitpaban Ghosh: A retired doctor (HOD, ENT-Surgeon) from prestigious medical institute, All Indian Institute of Medical Sciences, Delhi Mother- Shrimati Karuna Ghosh; House Maker

Spouse- Mrs. Donna Ghosh, B.Sc Zoology, Kerala University: House Maker.

Daughter- Ms Mrinalini Maria Ghosh, 9th Grade, Maneckji Cooper School, Mumbai